<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Accessibility | My blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://ferrous26.github.com/blog/categories/accessibility/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ferrous26.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-04T01:05:12-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ferrous26.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Rada]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accessibility: Keyboarding]]></title>
    <link href="http://ferrous26.github.com/blog/2012/04/03/axelements-part1/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ferrous26.github.com/blog/2012/04/03/axelements-part1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the first article in a short series about the different
components of
<a href="https://github.com/Marketcircle/AXElements">AXElements</a>. AXElements
has been rewritten to be much more modular and now various components
may be used individually. The keyboard event generator was the first
component to be polished and released as its own gem.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>Event generation is exposed via the
<a href="https://github.com/Marketcircle/AXElements/blob/master/lib/accessibility/string.rb">Accessibility::String</a>
mix-in. Using the mix-in, a simple string of human readable text is
taken and turned it into a sequence of events which may be fed to one
of the keyboard event posting APIs provided by OS X.</p>

<p>To get started you will need to have a working Ruby 1.9
implementation---I've tested this with MRI 1.9.3 and MacRuby (for
MacRuby you will need a <a href="http://www.macruby.org/files/nightlies/">nightly build</a>).
Then you can install the <code>AXTyper</code> gem:</p>

<p><code>bash
gem install AXTyper
</code></p>

<p><strong>UPDATE</strong>: The gem has been reported to not compile if your Ruby was
compiled with GCC. The preferred solution would be for you to
recompile Ruby with Clang or use MacRuby. 😝 I'm not a pro with C
extensions, but I'll look into whether or not I can force the
extension to compile with Clang for you people who do not want to, or
cannot, recompile with Clang.</p>

<p>The quickest demonstration of event generation is through <code>irb</code>:</p>

<p><code>ruby
irb(main):001:0&gt; require 'rubygems'
=&gt; true
irb(main):002:0&gt; require 'accessibility/string'
=&gt; true
irb(main):003:0&gt; include Accessibility::String
=&gt; NSObject
irb(main):004:0&gt; events = keyboard_events_for &quot;Hello, #{ENV['USER']}.&quot;
=&gt; [[56, true], [38, true], [38, false], [56, false], [2, true],
 [2, false], [35, true], [35, false], [35, true], [35, false],
 [1, true], [1, false], [13, true], [13, false], [49, true],
 [49, false], [46, true], [46, false], [31, true], [31, false],
 [0, true], [0, false], [4, true], [4, false], [0, true], [0, false],
 [14, true], [14, false]]
irb(main):005:0&gt;
</code></p>

<p>And now you have some events! Events are number/boolean tuples;
the number is a key code and the boolean is the key state; there are
more details regarding the key code, but I'll get to that later.</p>

<p>Now that we have some events, we should figure out what to do with
them since they are not of much use on their own. The most useful, and
easiest, thing to do is post them to the system. This of course comes
with a caveat: you will actually be causing the keys to be typed out
to the system and the front most application will receive the events.</p>

<p><strong>Be careful of the string you give to the generator!</strong></p>

<p>The interface for posting events is different depending on if you are
using MRI or MacRuby. With MacRuby, events can be posted natively in
Ruby code, but for this demonstration the C extension provided by
<code>AXTyper</code> includes a singleton method, <code>KeyCoder.post_event</code>, which
takes a single event and posts it to the system. Using this method we
can post our events:</p>

<p><code>ruby
irb(main):005:0&gt; events.each do |event| KeyCoder.post_event event end
Hello, mrada.=&gt; [[56, true], [38, true], [38, false], [56, false],
 [2, true], [2, false], [35, true], [35, false], [35, true],
 [35, false], [1, true], [1, false], [13, true], [13, false],
 [49, true], [49, false], [46, true], [46, false], [31, true],
 [31, false], [0, true], [0, false], [4, true], [4, false], [0, true],
 [0, false], [14, true], [14, false]]
irb(main):006:0&gt; Hello, mrada.
</code></p>

<p>You'll notice that typing begins immediately when the <code>post_event</code>
method is called. Typing is also really fast; in fact, it has to be
slowed down for practical use.</p>

<p>Let's add a wrapper to do generation and posting together, we'll
alsoadd a small time buffer so that you get a chance to release the
return key after entering a command in <code>irb</code>:</p>

<p><code>ruby
def type string
  sleep 0.1
  keyboard_events_for(string).each do |event|
    KeyCoder.post_event event
  end
end
</code></p>

<p>Now let's try something a bit more complicated:</p>

<p><code>ruby
type &quot;\\CONTROL+l `say 'ZOMG'`\n&quot;
</code></p>

<h2>A Little More Depth</h2>

<p>So what's going on here? On the AXElements side of things there is just
a basic lexer and generator. The lexer tokenizes the string input and
the generator takes the tokens and generates one or more pairs of
event tuples. The interesting detail is that a set of escape sequences
for control keys has been added.</p>

<h4>Lexing</h4>

<p>Strings fed to the lexer support an extra set of escape sequences for
the control keys like Control, Option, Command, etc.. The last example
above used the <code>&quot;\\CONTROL&quot;</code> escape sequence to represent the left
control key. Other than those special sequences, string formatting
is straight forward and you can use all the letters, numbers, and
symbols that you would in any other string. Uppercasing letters is
automatically handled for you and so are all of the symbols that you
would have to hold down the shift or option key in order to
type. White space and line breaks in strings will get turned into
tabs, spaces, and return/enter, and delete key presses appropriately,
but you can also use <code>&quot;\t&quot;</code>, <code>&quot;\s&quot;</code>, <code>&quot;\r&quot;</code>, <code>&quot;\n&quot;</code>, and <code>&quot;\b&quot;</code> as you
would in any other string.</p>

<p>Once the lexer is done lexing, its output is fed into the generator.</p>

<h4>Event Generation</h4>

<p>The event generator inspects each token and figures out what events
need to be generated in order type the token.</p>

<p>As mentioned above, events are number/boolean tuples. They are fed to
the
<a href="http://developer.apple.com/library/mac/#documentation/Carbon/Reference/QuartzEventServicesRef/Reference/reference.html">CGEventCreateKeyboardEvent()</a>
function that is used in the above examples. The function takes a key
code and a key state as parameters and so each event pair is simply
what is required to be passed to that function.</p>

<p>Key codes are a mapping of numbers to keys on the keyboard; some
mappings are static, such as the control keys; and some mappings are
dynamic based on the keyboard layout. Since a code refers to a
physical key and not the particular symbol they represent, upper case
letters require the generation of events for pressing either the shift
key before hitting the lower case letter.</p>

<p>The key state is simply a boolean value with <code>true</code> meaning that the
key is in the keydown state and <code>false</code> meaning that the key is in the
keyup state. This makes it possible to hold down the shift key and
then press the <code>&quot;a&quot;</code> key to generate an <code>&quot;A&quot;</code>; it also makes it
possible to simulate hotkeys and symbols.</p>

<h5>Symbols</h5>

<p>Symbols such as <code>&quot;!&quot;</code>, <code>&quot;∑&quot;</code>, and <code>&quot;]&quot;</code> are all supported by the event
generator. Any symbol that you can type directly using one or more
keys should <strong>Just Work™</strong>. Some contrived examples might look like
this snippet:</p>

<p><code>ruby
type &quot;@hash = { a: '∑', b: '™' }\n&quot;
type &quot;@hash.merge! { c: '£', d: '¢' }\n&quot;
type &quot;@hash.inspect\n&quot;
</code></p>

<p>A caveat to this is that some symbols can be on the keyboard twice,
the obvious cases are the mathematical operations and numbers. The
event generator does not use the keypad for plain symbols in
strings. To use the keypad keys specifically you will need to use
custom escape sequences.</p>

<h5>Escape Characters</h5>

<p>As mentioned above, standard escape codes (e.g. <code>&quot;\n&quot;</code>, <code>&quot;\t&quot;</code>) all still
work, even using <code>&quot;\b&quot;</code> as the delete key. On top of the built in escape
sequences, the lexer and generator have added an additional set of
escape sequences for control keys and other static keys. The full list
is located in the documentation
<a href="http://rdoc.info/github/Marketcircle/AXElements/master/Accessibility/String/EventGenerator#CUSTOM-constant">here</a>,
but the naming convention should be obvious enough after a small
demonstration.</p>

<p>```ruby
type &quot;\CONTROL&quot;</p>

<h1>or</h1>

<p>type &quot;\CTRL&quot;</p>

<h1>using built in escape codes</h1>

<p>type &quot;The cake is a lie\b\b\b\b\b\b delicious&quot;</p>

<h1>Use the CMD+a hotkey and then start typing</h1>

<p>type &quot;\COMMAND+a I just deleted everything, didn't I?&quot;</p>

<h1>type one key and then the other</h1>

<p>type &quot;\1 \+ \2 \n&quot;</p>

<h1>type all the keys as a hot key combination</h1>

<p>type &quot;\CMD+\SHIFT+s&quot;</p>

<h1>or</h1>

<p>type &quot;\CMD+S&quot;</p>

<h1>type out a backslash</h1>

<p>type &quot;\&quot;</p>

<h1>type out a fake command key</h1>

<p>type &quot;\CAKE&quot;
```</p>

<p>There are two rules to using the custom escape sequences. First, a
custom escape sequence must be terminated by an empty space <em>or</em> the
end of the string.</p>

<h6>Hot Keys</h6>

<p>The second rule is an exception to the first rule; a custom escape
sequence can end with a <code>&quot;+&quot;</code> if it is being used in a hot key
combination and will be immediately followed by another key in the
combination. In previous examples we combined two and three keys in
order to make a combination, but an upper limit on the number of keys
is not defined by the event generator.</p>

<h2>Sending Events To A Specific Application</h2>

<p>Though the easiest way to post events to the system was to use
<code>CGEventPost()</code>, there are also APIs for posting events to a specific
application regardless of which application is focused.</p>

<p>The API for doing this is located in the
<a href="http://developer.apple.com/library/mac/#documentation/Accessibility/Reference/AccessibilityLowlevel/AXUIElement_h">OS X Accessibility headers</a>,
but requires you to provide a reference to the application where you
would like to post events. Using the accessibility APIs is a little
tricky at first, especially in Ruby.</p>

<p>I'll cover Accessibility API basics in the next part of this series:
&quot;Accessibility: From References To Objects&quot;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
